Guide to the American Theological Library Association Records - Addendum B
Yale University Divinity School Library
American Theological Library Association Records - Addendum B
1996-2014
RG 163B
Yale University Divinity School Library
5.75
(14 boxes)
This record group represents the official archives of the American Theological Library Association. The archives include organizational and administrative records, board and committee records, materials from annual conferences, and ATLA publications primarily from the period 2000 to 2014. This is a second addendum to the material found in Record Group 163.
American Theological Library Association
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the American Theological Library Association, 2014.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
The mission of the American Theological Library Association (ATLA) is to foster the study of theology and religion by enhancing the development of theological and religious studies libraries and librarianship. Established in 1946, ATLA is governed by an elected board of directors and has over 800 individual, institutional, and affiliate members. See Record Groups 163 and 163a for information on the history of the American Theological Library Association. Dennis Norlin was Executive Director from 1995 until his retirement in 2010. Brenda Bailey-Hainer became Executive Director in December 2010.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Divinity Library was designated as the official repository for the archives of the American Theological Library Association in 2000. Record Group 163B is the second addendum to the original records received at that time. According to ATLA policy, records of the Board of Directors are sent directly to the archives at Yale Divinity Library while the ATLA's operational records are compiled by their on-site records manager and then sent to the Yale Divinity Library. For this reason the Board of Directors records in this collection extend into 2014 while ATLA operational records generally date up to 2009, with some publications and conference records dating to 2012. The series structure of this record group reflects ATLA's administrative organization.
Series I, Board of Directors, includes Board meeting agendas and minutes, as well as materials of the Board's Executive Committee. Since the dockets for Board meetings include reports documenting ATLA activities, this series provides a concise overview of the organization's work.
Series II, Departments, includes a sub-series for each department, arranged in alphabetical order by department name beginning with a sub-series for Executive Director files. Records of the Executive Director include correspondence, annual reports to the Board of Directors, and information regarding employment agreements. The remaining department sub-series are: Electronic Products and Services, Financial Services, Member Services, and Preservation. The Financial Services Department sub-series includes financial reports, statements and independent audits of the organization. Housed in the sub-series for Member Services are copies of the ATLA newsletters, Theological Librarianship Journal, Proceedings and other records of the ATLA's annual conferences, the ATLA Serials Exchange program (formerly known as the Library Materials Exchange program), additional ATLA publications, and records of the ATLA website. Materials regarding annual conference planning are filed under Series III, Committees of the Association, sub-series Annual Conference Committee. The sub-series for the ATLA Serials Exchange Department includes correspondence and database design proposals. Preservation Department records include correspondence.
Series III, Committees of the Association, includes sub-series for each type of committee in ATLA: committees appointed by the Executive Director, joint committees established by the Board, advisory committees, and special committees and standing committees of the Board. Within each sub-series, the committees are arranged alphabetically by committee name. Committees appointed by the Executive Director include: Annual Conference Committee, Education Committee, Emergency Response Team Committee, Endowment Committee, Enterprise Content Management Committee, Historic/Archives Committee, International Collaboration Committee, Local Host Committee, Professional Development Committee, Publications Committee, and Supervisor Evaluation Task Force Committee. Joint committees established by the Board includes the Committee on Standards for Regional Groups in ATLA. Advisory committees include: Preservation Advisory Committee and the Technology Advisory Committee. Special committees and standing committees of the Board include: Nominating Committee, Tellers Committee, and the ATLA/ATS Digital Standards and Projects Committee.
Series IV, Interest Groups, contains records of ATLA's Interest Groups, includes a sub-series General containing correspondence to all Interest Groups, followed by sub-series arranged in alphabetical order by group name, including: Automation and Technology, Collection Evaluation and Development, College and University, Lesbian and Gay, OCLC Theological User Group, Public Services, Publications, and Technical Services.
Series V, Affiliated Institutions and Organizations, includes a file containing materials regarding BETH, Bibliothèques Européennes de Théologie.
Series VI, Audio-visual materials, contains photographs and ephemera from various ATLA events between 2000 and 2004.
Arrangement
I. Board of Directors, 1996-2014
II. Departments, 1999-2013
III. Committees of the Association, 2000-2007
IV. Interest Groups, 2000-2012
V. Affiliated Institutions and Organizations, 2010
VI. Audio-visual materials, 2000-2004
Libraries -- Special collections -- Religion; Library science -- Societies, etc.; American Theological Library Association
- Board of Directors, 1996-2018; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Financial audits and reports distributed to the Board at meetings are filed under Series II: Departments: Financial Services
  - Regarding governance
    - Correspondence and research re: Carver Workshop and Policy Governance, 1996-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reports to the Board
    - Report of Board's Direct Inspection Team, member services, 2008 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Financial report 2007 December 26, 2008 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Duplicate copy located in Series II: Departments: Financial Services Department
    - Reports to the Board re: Executive Director Evaluation 2001-2007, 2007 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Conditions Governing Access
      INCLUDES EVALUATIONS FOR 2001, 2004, 2005, 2007 - RESTRICTED UNTIL OCTOBER 2021
    - Additional reports, 2008 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes Endowment Committee report, proposed amendment to ATLA Board Policy Manual, exit interview form, talking points re: executive director evaluation process, salary comparison spreadsheet
  - Election documentation
    - Teller's Committee report to Board re: election results, 2006 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence to newly-elected Board members, 2006 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Teller's Committee report to Board re: election results, 2007 March 7 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to newly-elected Board members, 2007 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual Conference Board meeting, June 2007
    - Docket (includes agenda, draft minutes from previous Board meeting, reports to Board from Executive Director and committees, financial statements, appendices), 2007 June 13-17 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Minutes of business meeting at annual conference, 2007 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors meeting (approved version), 2007 June 13-17 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Midwinter Board meeting, January 2008
    - Agenda and delineation of Board president responsibilities, 2008 January 16-19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Docket, 2008 January 17-19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Minutes of executive session meetings, 2008 January 18-19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minutes of Board of Directors meeting, 2008 January 17-19 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Election documentation
    - Teller's Committee report to Board re: election results, 2008 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence to newly-elected Board members, 2008 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Annual conference Board meeting, June 2008
    - Docket, 2008 June 25-28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Minutes of business meetings at conference, 2008 June 26 and 28 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Minutes of executive session meeting, 2008 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Board materials and reports, 2008 June 25-26 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Includes: board agenda with notes, morning worship program June 26 2008, business meeting agenda June 26 2008, revised ATS statistics form, press release re: partnership with EBSCO June 25 2008, Audit Committee report, report of the Special Committee on Diversity, report of the Executive Director evaluation process task force, proposed procedure for Executive Director evaluation, Annual Conference Committee report re: 2011 conference site, Secretary's Report, Endowment Committee report, Preservation Interest Group organizational statement, ATLA 2009 conference status report
    - Minutes of Board of Directors meeting, 2008 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence and documents
    - Correspondence to Board from Executive Director re: U.S. financial crisis, 2008 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Summary of Board meeting re: policy governance, 2008 October 4-5 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence from Board to Executive Director re: PeopleWorks performance evaluation, 2008 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      FILE RESTRICTED UNTIL DECEMBER 31 2018
  - Midwinter Board meeting, January 2009
    - Docket, 2009 January 15-17 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Minutes of the executive sessions, 2009 January 15-17 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Board materials and reports, 2009 January 15-17 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      File Plan
      Includes: Autdit Committee report and financial statements, Endowment Fund report, conflict of interest policy, whistleblower policy, record retention schedule
      Financial report dated January 14, 2009 distributed to Board at Januar 2009 meeting filed under Series II: Departments: Financial Services Department
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2009 January 15-17 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Additional Board materials
    - Conflict of interest questionnaires, 2009 January 22 - February 3 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Scenarios for the Association's future, 2009 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Sent to the Board by Executive Director Dennis Norlin
  - Annual Conference Board meeting, June 2009
    - Docket, 2009 June 17-21 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Minutes of the executive session, 2009 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2009 June 17, 21 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence
    - Request to share salary guidelines and principles, 2009 July 1 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Request to share salary guidelines and principles sent to Board by Executive Director Dennis Norlin July 1 2009.
    - Email correspondence re: Financial Services Director resignation, 2009 September 17, 19 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Includes emails from Dennis Norlin to ATLA staff and Roberta Schaafsma regarding resignation of Financial Services Director
  - Direct Inspection team materials
    - Correspondence to ATLA headquarters staff from Direct Inspection team, 2009 September (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Report of Direct Inspection team triennial review of personnel, 2009 October 15 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Midwinter Board meeting, January 2010
    - Docket, 2010 January 14-16 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Minutes of the Executive Sessions, 2010 January 15-16 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Board materials and reports, 2010 January (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Includes: Endowment Committee report January 8 2010, ATLA 2013 Conference overview, Audit Committee report - preliminary draft, financial statements August 31 2009 - preliminary draft, draft revision to Interest Group handbook, ATLA Organizational Ends - adopted by Board January 14 2009
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2010 January 14-16 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Conflict of interest questionnaires, 2010 January 15 - June 20 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence
    - Memo: update to Board re: OCLC/EBSCO transition, 2010 April 1 (Box 2, Folder 45)
      Memo to Board from Dennis Norlin re: OCLC/EBSCO transition dated April 6 2010 with accompanying email correspondence to Board from President David Stewart dated April 1 2010
    - Email correspondence re: Executive Director's departure, 2010 April 27 - June 13 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      RESTRICTED UNTIL JUNE 13,2020
    - Email correspondence re: Print on Demand, 2010 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Email correspondence from President David Stewart to Chicago Law Partners, 2010 May 18 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      Email from ATLA Board President David Stewart to Jim Mandel at Chicago Law Partners, LLC
    - Email correspondence and engagement letter with Chicago Law Partners, 2010 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Email correspondence re. resignation of Board member, 2010 July 1 (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Email from ATLA librarian Laura C. Wood to ATLA Board re: David Stewart resignation
  - Agreements of the Board
    - Separation Agreement and General Release for Executive Director, 2010 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 56A)
    - Search Agreement with Tuft Associates Inc., 2010 June 7 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Annual Conference Board meeting, June 2010
    - Docket, 2010 June 16-20 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Minutes of the business meeting at conference, 2010 June 17 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2010 June 16-20 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Tufts Associates Executive Director search materials, 2010 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence and documents
    - Sealed documents, 2010 July 13 (Box 2, Folder 57)
      TO REMAIN RESTRICTED UNTIL JULY 13, 2020
    - Minutes of Board conference call re. resignation of Board member, 2010 July 28 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Engagement Letter with Legacy Professionals LLP re: financial audit, 2010 October 25 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Fall Board Meeting, November 2010
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2010 November 6-7 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Minutes of the Executive Sessions, 2010 November 6-7 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Minutes re: interview of candidates for Executive Director position RESTRICTED UNTIL NOVEMBER 7, 2020
    - Action submitted by Department of Financial Services re: Morgan Stanley Smith Barney, 2010 November 7 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Department of Financial Services submitted action to Board for approval regarding removal of Dennis Norlin as signatory of Morgan Stanley Smith Barney Endownment Account and Scholarship and Grant Fund Account and addition of Marie Jacobsen's signature. Action was approved November 7 2010.
    - Action submitted by Department of Financial Services re: TIAA CREF tax deferred annuity plan, 2010 November 7 (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Department of Financial Services submitted action to Board for approval regarding approval of TIAA CREF tax deferred annuity plan. Action was approved November 7 2010.
    - Document packet for Executive Director candidates, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Midwinter Board Meeting, January 2011
    - Docket, 2011 January 13-15 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Minutes of the executive session, 2011 January 14 (Box 2, Folder 66)
      RESTRICTED UNTIL JANUARY 14 2021
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2011 January 13-15 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Audit and report from Legacy Professionals LLP, 2011 January 14 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Existence and Location of Originals
      File contains cover letter and summary of financial audit for year ending August 31, 2010. Actual report filed under Series II: Departments: Financial Services Department
    - Direction Inspection report: Member Services department, 2011 January 12 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Conflict of interest questionnaires, 2011 January 13-14 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Reports and minutes of interim executive sessions, 2011
    - Report from Survey and Ballot systems re: election, 2011 March 2 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Minutes of executive session conference call, 2011 April 28 (Box 3, Folder 72)
      TO BE RESTRICTED UNTIL APRIL 28 2021
    - Minutes of executive session conference call, 2011 May 26 (Box 3, Folder 73)
      TO BE RESTRICTED UNTIL MAY 26 2021
  - Annual Conference Board Meeting, June 2011
    - Docket, 2011 June 7-12 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Minutes of executive session meeting, 2011 June 8 (Box 3, Folder 75)
      TO BE RESTRICTED UNTIL JUNE 8, 2021
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2011 June 8-12 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Documents and minutes of interim board meetings, 2011
    - Minutes of the Board conference call, 2011 October 19 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Resolution of Corporation, 2011 November 16 (Box 3, Folder 78)
      Adds James Butler, Director of Information Systems as check signer.
    - Minutes of Board email meeting, 2011 December 16-19 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Midwinter Board meeting, January 2012
    - Docket, 2012 January 11-14 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Minutes of executive session, 2012 January 13 (Box 3, Folder 81)
      TO BE RESTRICTED UNTIL JANUARY 13 2022
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2012 January 12-14 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Conflict of interest questionnaires, 2012 January 12-14 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Reports and minutes of interim Board meetings, 2012
    - Minutes of Board online voting email, 2012 January 16-19 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Report from Survey & Ballot systems re: election, 2012 March 2 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Minutes of Board conference call, 2012 March 23 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Minutes of Board online meeting (email), 2012 May 15-16 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Annual Conference Board meeting, June-July 2012
    - Docket, 2012 June 27 - July 1 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Minutes of business meetings at conference, 2012 June 27-29 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2012 Jun 27 - July 1 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Midwinter Board Meeting, February 2013
    - Docket, 2013 February 7-9 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2013 February 7-9 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Reports to the Board, 2013 February 7 (Box 3, Folder 93)
      Includes Finance Committee Report to Board and Endowment Fund documents
  - Minutes of interim Board meetings, 2013
    - Minutes of the Board meeting conference call, 2013 April 3 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Annual Conference Board Meeting, June 2013
    - Docket, 2013 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Minutes of business meeting at conference, 2013 June 20 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Minutes of the Executive Session, 2013 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2013 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Report of the 2012 ATLA Preservation Survey, 2013 June 19 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Fall Board Meeting, October 2013
    - Docket, 2013 October 16-19 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2013 October 18-19 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Midwinter Board Meeting, February 2014
    - Docket, 2014 February 20-22 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2014 February 20-22 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Reports to the Board, 2014 February 21 (Box 3, Folder 104)
      Includes Communication and Counsel to Board regarding new potential competitor to ATLA RDB and ATLA CPLI, update on new production platform, Diversity in Theological Librarianship pamphlet.
  - Annual Conference Board Meeting, June 2014
    - Docket, 2014 June 16-18 (Box 14, Folder 253)
    - Minutes of Executive Session, 2014 June 17 (Box 14, Folder 254)
  - Fall Board Meeting, October 2014
    - Docket, 2014 October 16-18 (Box 14, Folder 255)
      Docket includes approved minutes of June 2014 Board meeting as the Board had moved to new system of approving meeting minutes via email. Prior to this time, the minutes in the Dockets for the previous meetings were draft minutes, to be approved at the Board meeting.
    - Minutes of Executive Session, 2014 October 17 (Box 14, Folder 256)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors meeting, 2014 October 17-18 (Box 14, Folder 257)
    - "Strategic Thinking and Direction Setting" session presentation, facilitated by Tecker International; Draft Strategic Plan for ATLA, 2014 October 16 (Box 14, Folder 258)
    - "In Good Faith: Collection Care, Preservation, and Access in Small Theological and Religious Studies Libraries Survey Report", 2014 September (Box 14, Folder 259)
    - Executive Director report, 2014 October 15 (Box 14, Folder 260)
- Departments, 1999-2014; Series II
  - Executive Director records
    - Annual reports of the Executive Director
      - Annual report 2004-2005, 2006 January (Box 4, Folder 105)
      - Annual report 2005-2006, 2007 January (Box 4, Folder 106)
      - Annual report 2006-2007, 2008 January (Box 4, Folder 107)
      - Annual report 2007-2008, 2009 January (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Executive Director Employment Agreement and Compensation 1999-2006
      - 78th Annual Compensation and Benefit Survey, 1999 November (Box 4, Folder 109)
      - Correspondence November 1999, 1999 November 10 (Box 4, Folder 110)
      - Correspondence and research December 1999, 1999 December (Box 4, Folder 111)
      - Employment Agreement drafts and correspondence 2000, 2000 August 31-October 17 (Box 4, Folder 112)
      - Employment Agreement, 2001 January 20 (Box 4, Folder 113)
      - Correspondence March 2001, 2001 March 1 (Box 4, Folder 114)
      - Correspondence and research 2005, 2005 October 28-November 30 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Correspondence re: IFLA Theological Library Association section, 2002 April 25-May 5 (Box 4, Folder 116)
      Includes IFLA Statutes and Rules of Procedure adopted August 13 2000 and registered with Chamber of Commerce, The Hague, Netherlands July 18 2001
    - Memory book commemorating Executive Director Dennis Norlin, 2013 August (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Electronic Products and Services Department
    - Product support
      - ATLA religious database sampler on CD-ROM, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 118)
        Includes two copies of CD-ROM sampler.
  - Financial Services Department
    - Financial report for the period November 2007 (and 2006), 2007 December 26 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Financial report for the period September 2008 (and 2007), 2009 January 14 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Audit Committee report 2009
      - Audit Committee prelimiary draft report, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 121)
      - Financial statements, 2009 August 31 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Financial statements and report of independent auditor by Legacy Professionals LLP, 2011 January 14 (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Financial statements and report of independent auditor Legacy Professionals LLP, 2012 January 12 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Financial report by independent auditor McGladrey LLP, 2013 August 31 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Financial report by independent auditor McGladrey LLP, 2014 January 13 (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Member Services Department
    - Newsletters
      - Newsletter procedures and correspondence, 2005 October 26 (Box 6, Folder 143)
      - Newsletter, volume 54, numbers 1-2, 2006 November, 2007 February (Box 6, Folder 144)
      - Newsletter, volume 54, numbers 3-4, 2007 May, November (Box 6, Folder 145)
      - Newsletter, volume 55, numbers 1-2, 2007 November, 2008 February (Box 6, Folder 146)
      - Newsletter, volume 55, numbers 3-4, 2008 May, August (Box 6, Folder 147)
      - Newsletter, volume 56, numbers 1-11, 2008 November - 2009 October (Box 6, Folder 148)